You've learned a lot of Python so far.
لقد تعلمت الكثير من Python حتى الآن.
You know how to represent numerical and text data and you know
تَعرف كيفية تمثيل البيانات الرقمية والنصية وتعرف كيفية
how to store collections of data in lists, sets and dictionaries.
تخزين مجموعات من البيانات في القوائم والمجموعات والقواميس.
Yes, you've collected a set of tools for working with data.
نعم، لقد قمت بجمع مجموعة من الأدوات للعمل مع البيانات.
You can use Python's built-in methods and
يمكنك استخدام أساليب ودوال Python المدمجة،
functions and you can write functions of your own.
ويمكنك كتابة دوال خاصة بك.
You can iterate with loops and make conditional decisions with if and else.
يمكنك التكرار مع الحلقات واتخاذ قرارات شرطية مع أي شيء آخر.
With these tools, you can solve most programming problems.
باستخدام هذه الأدوات، يمكنك حل معظم مشاكل البرمجة.
Sure, there's more to Python than all we've covered
بالتأكيد، هناك الكثير من Python بخلاف ما قمنا بتغطيته
so far and we'll get two more topics later on.
حتى الآن وسنتناول موضوعين آخرين في وقت لاحق.
But now, it's time to apply the skills you've
ولكن الآن، حان الوقت لتطبيق المهارات التي
learned so you can practice the craft of programming.
تعلمتها حتى تتمكن من ممارسة حرفة البرمجة.
That's right. Programming is more than just syntax.
هذا صحيح. البرمجة أكثر من مجرد تركيب.
To solve a problem you need to define it first.
لحل مشكلة تحتاج إلى تعريفها أولاً.
For example, you'll need to think about inputs to
فعلى سبيل المثال، ستحتاج إلى التفكير في مدخلات
the program and the results that you should give as output.
للبرنامج والنتائج التي يجب أن تعطيها كمخرجات.
Once you thought through the goals of your program,
بمجرد التفكير في أهداف برنامجك،
you need to think about how to break the program down into smaller pieces.
تحتاج إلى التفكير في كيفية تقسيم البرنامج إلى أجزاء أصغر.
Then, you need to evaluate your plan to make sure it solves the original problem.
بعد ذلك، تحتاج إلى تقييم خطتك للتأكد من أنها تحل المشكلة الأصلية.
I often find that when I plan a new program,
وكثيراً ما أجد أنه عندما أخطط لبرنامج جديد،
I realize that the problem is more complicated than I had assumed.
فإنني أدرك أن المشكلة أكثر تعقيدًا مما كنت أتوقعه.
Planning before coding, helps me understand the problem better.
التخطيط قبل الترميز، يساعدني على فهم المشكلة بشكل أفضل.
There are other things to keep in mind when you do begin coding.
هناك أشياء أخرى يجب وضعها في الاعتبار عند بدء الترميز.
You want to write some test cases so that you
تحتاج إلى كتابة بعض حالات الاختبار بحيث
can check that your code does what it's supposed to do.
يمكنك التحقق من أن الرموز الخاصة بك تقوم بما يفترض القيام به.
You also need to make your code readable.
تحتاج أيضا إلى جعل الرموز الخاصة بك قابلة للقراءة.
If your code is so complicated that you could only just understand it,
إذا كان التعليمة البرمجية معقدًا للغاية بحيث يمكنك فقط فهمها،
as you write it, you have no hope of understanding it later on.
وأنت تكتبها، فلا تأمل في فهمها لاحقًا.
Before we move on to the next topics,
قبل الانتقال إلى الموضوعات التالية،
there will be a lab that let's you practice these skills.
سيكون هناك مختبر يتيح لك ممارسة هذه المهارات.
Good luck. As you work,
حظًا سعيدًا. أثناء عملكم،
remember to break problems into smaller pieces,
تذكروا حل المشكلات إلى أجزاء أصغر،
to plan, and to focus on readability. We'll see you soon.
للتخطيط، وأيضًا التركيز على قابلية القراءة. نراكم قريبًا في ذلك الدرس.